Guide to the Ellsworth Milton and Alice Statler papers, 1896-1961.
Milton, Ellsworth and Statler, Alice papers, 1896-1961.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ellsworth Milton and Alice Statler papers, 1896-1961.
3879
Ellsworth Milton Statler, 1863-1928.
4.5 cubic ft.
Company documents, scrapbooks and letters.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes some original Hotels Statler Company documents; stockholders lists, 1914-1917; two scrapbooks of E. M. Statler obituaries, 1928; photocopy of the Statler's will; two scrapbooks of clippings and letters about Alice (Mrs. E. M.) Statler; Statler Hotels Delaware Corporation documents; and other scrapbooks and documents. Also includes 78 rpm phonograph records.
Also, a four-page hand-written letter dated March 29, 1918 from E. M. Statler to Frank A. McKowne, who was serving in the American Expeditionary Forces in France. Frank McKowne was the assistant to Mr. Statler beginning in 1914 and served as president of the Hotels Statler from 1928 until his retirement in 1945.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes some original Hotels Statler Company documents; stockholders lists, 1914-1917; two scrapbooks of E. M. Statler obituaries, 1928; photocopy of the Statler's will; two scrapbooks of clippings and letters about Alice (Mrs. E. M.) Statler; Statler Hotels Delaware Corporation documents; and other scrapbooks and documents. Also includes 78 rpm phonograph records.
Also, a four-page hand-written letter dated March 29, 1918 from E. M. Statler to Frank A. McKowne, who was serving in the American Expeditionary Forces in France. Frank McKowne was the assistant to Mr. Statler beginning in 1914 and served as president of the Hotels Statler from 1928 until his retirement in 1945.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Statler, Ellsworth Milton, 1863-1928.; Statler, Alice.; Hotels Statler Company.; Statler Hotels Delaware Corporation.
Subjects:
Hotels.
Form and Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Documents and Miscellany
Boxes 1-5, 7-8, a volume and a folder
Series II. Records
Boxes 6-7 and a volume
Series III. Tape Recordings
tr-10561a and tr-1062a
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Documents and Miscellany
  - 1 envelope of Hotels Statler Company, Inc. Original documents (see attached list). (Box 1)
  - 1 folder of Stockholders' Lists., 1914-1917 (Box 1)
  - 2 scrapbooks of E.M. Statler obituaries., 1928 (Box 1)
  - 2 scrapbooks of clippings and letters about Mrs. E.M. (Alice) Statler. (Box 1)
  - 1 volume of "Bulletin for Department Meetings.", 1921-1928 (Box 1)
  - 1 volume of Statler Hotels Delaware Corporation, "Certain Basic Corporate Documents.", 1954 (Box 1)
  - 1 folder of General-Corporate Organization Papers. (Box 1)
  - 1 folder, photostatic copy of E.M. Statler's will, 9 pp., 1927-11-17 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook., 1896-1901 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook., 1901-1904 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook., 1925-1928 (Box 2)
  - 2 Special Award Certificates., 1956, 1961 (Box 2)
  - 1 large tribute book for E.M. Statler., 1928 (Volume 2)
  - Mostly all photographs., 1922-1955 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, typescript of The Statler Story by A.M. Statler, and misc. (Box 4)
  - Awards and phonograph recordings. (Box 5)
  - EM Statler Mason certificate, award (Box 7)
  - Accounting Records, Hotel Statler, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Four-page hand-written letter from E. M. Statler to Frank A. McKowne - manuscript folder, 1918-03-29; Single Folder
  - Binder "From the Files of E.M. Statler" presented to the Hotel School by Mrs. E.M. Statler, no date (Box 8)
  - "Hotel Man of the Half Century", by Kate D. Davis - article reprinted from the Southern Hotel Journal, 1950-03 (Box 8)
- Series II. Records
  - Album of (8) 78 RPM phonograph records. (Volume 1)
  - EM Statler, "Let's Dramatize Our Work", 1937 (Box 6)
  - EM Statler, "Indifference to Guests", 1938 (Box 6)
  - EM Statler, "A Good Disposition is a Good Asset", 1939 (Box 6)
  - EM Statler, "Guests who Refuse to be Satisfied--And Our Service Report System", 1940 (Box 6)
  - EM Statler, "A Letter of Robert E. Lee to his Son", 1941 (Box 6)
  - Pan American Coffee Bureau, "Coffee Please!", 1942 (Box 6)
  - General Foods Corporation: An Institutional Food Service Division Presentation. "The Successful Waitress." Part 2, 1943 (Box 6)
  - "The Holiday Inn Maid.", 1944 (Box 6)
  - Special Education Program of Hotel Greeters of America, prepared by Lewis. "The Over-eager Cook","The Abandoned Baby.", 1945 (Box 6)
  - "Handling without Hands", Metropolitan Wire Goods Corp., 1946 (Box 6)
  - General Food Corporation, "The Successful Waitress" Part 1, 1947 (Box 6)
  - "Handling Without Hands", 1948 (Box 6)
  - Sarra, Inc. "A Career with Standard", 1949 (Box 6)
  - WHCU Ithaca, "How not to--How to Interview", 1950 (Box 6)
  - Vitrola, Ave Maria (Schubert-Wilhelm), 1951 (Box 6)
  - "The Guest who Didn't Check-out","The Too Friendly Reservation.", 1952 (Box 6)
  - "The Phoney Friend","The Banquet Speakers' Rooms", 1953 (Box 6)
  - "Emily Kimbrough Program" - Jonathan Harding (2 LPs), 1953-07-31; 6342 (Box 6)
  - "The Unwanted Four: Germs that cause Food Poisoning", National Restaurant Association, 1954 (Box 6)
  - "The Freeloaders: Food Service Pest Control", National Restaurant Association, 1955 (Box 6)
  - "It's Yours at the Statler" (2 copies), 1968; 1956 (Box 6)
  - "Statler Roundup", parts 5-6, 1946; 1957 (Box 6)
  - "Statler Roundup", parts two, three, seven, ten, eleven, 6331-6335 (Box 6)
  - Coffee Brewing Institute, "Speciality of the House" Urn Method for Brewing Coffee", "Specialty of the House: Vacuum Method for Brewing Coffee", 1958 (Box 7)
  - Liberty Mutual Insurance, "Smoothing the Flow of Restaurant Hospitality", 1944-11-13; 1959 (Box 7)
  - American Hotel Association, "Every Employee a Salesman", 1960 (Box 7)
  - Stouffer Restaurant Corporation, "Food for Thought", 1961 (Box 7)
  - American Hotel Association, "Fire Prevention", 1962 (Box 7)
  - American Hotel Association, "Food Service", 1963 (Box 7)
  - "American Hotel Association, "Preparing the Guest Room", 1964 (Box 7)
  - American Hotel Association, "Rooming the Guest", 1965 (Box 7)
  - American Hotel Association, "Front Office Courtesy", 1966 (Box 7)
  - "Change on the Table" - Waitress Training - Readers' Digest Presentation (includes filmstrip in box 8), 1969; 6336 (Box 6)
  - "The Magic Touch - Parts I and II - American Hotel and Motel Association (includes filmstrips in box 8), 1968; 6337-6338 (Box 6)
  - "I Like People" - Parts I and II - American Hotel and Motel Association (includes filmstrips in box 8), 1968; 6339-6340 (Box 6)
  - "Investing in People" - National Restaurant Association (includes filmstrip in box 8), 6341 (Box 6)
- Series III. Tape Recordings
  - Statler Roundup, 1946-02-07; 10561a
  - Statler Talk #5 - "It's Yours at the Statler", 10562a